Mss.940.M68
American Philosophical Society
Account of some campaigns of the British army from 1689 to 1712 and a journal of a campaign under Prince Eugene on the Upper Rhine, 1689-1735
Mss.940.M68
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 224 p.
Included in this volume are short treatises on military topics, such as fortification and geometry, and military discipline; an account of campaigns (1689-1697) with the Royal Regiment of Foot in Ireland; an account of campaigns under Prince Eugene of Savoy (1735), with lists of troops; a section entitled "Un traittes touchant les conquètes quon pouroit faire en Amerique sur la maison de Bourbon au cas que la querre devienne generale et qui seules peuvent retablir lequilibre de l'Europe;" and lists of imperial regiments.
1 volume, 224 p.
Crawford, John Lindsay,Earl of,1702-1749.
Volume 1
Scope and Contents note
The maps in the volume were drawn by Henry Kopp, secretary and draughtsman for Lord Crawford. They are inscribed to George II, king of England; Lord Loudoun, etc.
The actual dates on which the maps were drawn is conjectural. These volumes were most probably prepared for Earl Crawford between 1743 and 1747 so they could be better seen and studied in the family's muniment room.
Biographical/Historical note
John Lindsay, earl of Crawford and Lindsay (1702-1749), was a soldier. A Scotsman, he fought all over Europe. He was a captain in the British army and was permitted to join the Imperial army under Prince Eugene. In 1738 he received the rank of general from the Czarina Anna and fought against the Turks. He returned to the imperial forces and continued to fight until the Peace of London of 1748.
Related Archival Materials note
Lindsay's papers are continued in other manuscript volumes held by the APS: Journal of a campaign with the Russian army against Turkey, 1739 (Mss. 947 J82); Journal of a voyage from the Thames to Russia, and of campaigning with the Russian army, 1738-1739 (Mss. 947 L64).
Existence and Location of Copies note
Much of this volume, along with the other manuscript volumes of Lindsay's papers, were reproduced by Richard Rolt, Memoirs of the life of the Right. Hon. John Lindsay, Earl of Crawford and Lindsay (London: 1753).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Purchased from the library of Benjamin Franklin, 1803; accessioned, 1900 (33918).
Early American History Note
This is one of four large volumes that were part of Benjamin Franklin's personal library. The four volumes comprise a series of John Lindsay Crawford’s travels with the Russian Army from 1737-1739. The books have large maps of Europe.
Eugene, -- of Savoy, Prince of Savoy, -- 1663-1736.; Beyond Early America; Fortification.; Great Britain -- History, Military.; Ireland -- History -- War of 1689-1691.; Journals (notebooks).; Manuscript Essays; Maps.; Military discipline.; Military History; Military history, Modern -- 17th century.; Military history, Modern -- 18th century.; Military Records; Sketches.; Travel Narratives and Journals
- Maps
  - Plan et situation du Rhin et de ses environs jusque'au [sic] Coblenz, 1743-1747; 1 map, 175.9 x 85.7 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Scope and Contents note
    Colored.
    Other Finding Aids note
    Realms of Gold, 29 (1).
  - Plan et situation du Camp... entre les Villages Sertzenich et Trierweiller, 1743-1747; 1 map, 33.6 x 23.5 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (2).
  - Plan et situation du Camp de l'Infant; Imper[ator]; et Auxil; près d'Ering, 1743-1747; 1 map, 23.5 x 31.1 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (3).
  - Plan et situation du Camp de Bicon, 1743-1747; 1 map, 35.6 x 25.4 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (4).
  - Plan et situation du Camp des Imper[ator]: le long de la Rivier Salme entre les villages Ribnich et Salmerohr, 1743-1747; 1 map, 34.3 x 24.1 cm, with insert, 19 x 17.1 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (5).
  - De Vauban's design for fortification, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (6).
  - Baron de Cochorn's design for fortification, 1743-1747; 1 map, 22.9 x 36.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (7).
  - Imperial troops near Mayence, 1743-1747; 1 map, 38.7 x 27.3 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (8).
  - Plan et situation du Camp de Bingen, 1743-1747; 1 map, 39.4 x 26 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (9).
  - Plan et situation du Camp des Imper[ator]: près de Bretzenheim sur La Nahe, 1743-1747; 1 map, 35 x 24.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (10).
  - Plan et situation du Camp des Imper[ator]: près de Durrenbach, 1743-1747; 1 map, 35 x 23.5 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (11).
  - Plan et situation du Camp des Camp des Allies près de Simmern, 1743-1747; 1 map, 34.2 x 24.8 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (12).
  - Plan et situation du Camp des Imper[ator]; près de Hirschfeld, 1743-1747; 1 map, 35 x 22.9 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (13).
  - Plan et situation du Camp près de Monsfeld, 1743-1747; 1 map, 33 x 22.9 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (14).
  - Plan et situation du Camp près de Muhlheim, 1743-1747; 1 map, 35.6 x 25.4 cm; Kopp, Henry
    Realms of Gold, 29 (15).
- Treatises on Military Topics
  - Account of the campaigns from 1702-to 1712
    D. 64p.,F. Printed in part in Rolt, Memoirs of the life of John Lindsay. See J.G.Rosengarten, APS Proc., v.42, 397-404.
  - An account of the most remarkable transactions...
    from the year 1689 to...1697. D. 22p.,F. Printed in part in Roth, Memoirs of the life of John Lindsay. See J.G.Rosengarten, APS Proc., v.42, 397-404.
  - A method of discipline proposed for the behavior of a regiment of foot upon action.
    D. 29p., F. Printed in part in Roth, Memoirs of the life of John Lindsay. See J.Gl Rosengarten, APS Proc., vol. 42, 397-404.
  - A short treatise of fortification & geometry.
    D. 34p., F. Printed in part in Roth, Memoirs of the life of John Lindsay. See J.G.Rosengarten, APS Proc., v.42, 397-404.
  - March [route] ordered by Prince Eugene..., 1734
    D. 5p.,F. Printed in part: Roth,Memoirs of the life of John Lindsay. See J.G.Rosengarten, APS Proc.,v.42,397-404.
  - Journal of a campaign made with the imperial army under the command of Prince Eugene of Savoy on theUpper Rhine..., 1735
    D. 65p.maps, F. Printed in part: Roth,Memoirs of the life of John Lindsay. See J.G.Rosengarten, APS Proc.,v.42,397-404.